howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show.com that's Jim ruts show com
today's guest is John Rob thinker and
writer about global level systems
strategies and complex his main platform
these days its global gorillas on
patreon if you like his work please
support him on patreon I do he's a voice
worth having so John the reason I
reached out to you initially for this
brief second visit to our extra Koba 19
episodes I was a tweet that you made the
other day which I'll read one of the
most lasting effects of the pandemic
question mark the accelerated emergence
of the new political spectrum network
consensus versus networked dissent could
you say some more about that yeah one of
the things I've been writing about for a
long while is the emergence of a new
decision-making system a new social
decision-making system that can you know
over time as we kind of get our arms
around it complement the other social
decision-making systems that we have you
know we have tribalism which is
nationalism we have bureaucracy and we
have markets and we've tamed them more
or less over the last of five centuries
to effectively allow us to deal with
environmental challenges and now that
we're in a global environment a complex
global environment where the threats
have become more difficult to deal with
it seems that that you know the threats
are exceeding our capacity to make
effective decisions using the old
methods
and we need a new one this network
decision-making but you know trying to
figure out what it can be good for and
what it what it is bad at it will take
some time the model that I've developed
and that I've you know teased out of
what I've seen is that this network one
of the key decision-making systems that
that's falling out of it is this idea of
the consensus and dissent and the
consensus is an agreement on a very
simple proposition and it's allows
society to move very quickly once it
agrees on that proposition and the
dissent is this very similar to what you
see with you know a lot of what Trump
does it's always finding kind of the
opposite view and trying to disrupt
through you know different means the the
consensus a consensus set from the
outside appears to be detrimental to the
health and well-being of the people or
dissenting so in the case of in the
situation we're in right now with the
the pandemic we see a very clear example
of a consensus developing in terms of
you know this pandemic is bad and and
that we should eradicate it and it
developed very very quickly and then it
allowed the shutdown of the the entire
US economy to occur within weeks long
before the government's actually even
got to the point where they were
starting to order shutdowns so the
consensus actually you know shut down
air travel even though there really
isn't any restrictions under trouble now
it's done ninety six percent from where
it was it has shut down Commerce it
changed corporate behavior you know
through pressure both demand pressure
plus internal kind of social pressure to
force people to or force companies to
opt for work at home corporate travel
etc and then there now we have the
dissent is the group of people on the
outside who are saying let's let's open
up the economy now the pandemic is over
state
that it's a lot of the information is
faked or the goalposts are moving or
that we should go through with a herd
immunity strategy so that kind of
dynamic between dissent and consensus is
how we're making decisions now yeah it's
very very right yeah I love the point
that you make that in some sense the
social distancing at least the wave
started before the government acted you
know for instance you know I read the
signals and concluded it for myself and
my family we were locking the fuck down
around the 5th of March right along
great any state did it and so I was an
incremental Network signal and I passed
that word along to my friends and and at
least to some degree on social media and
so the network itself started these
parts but coalesced around a consensus
and you know I might been wrong but a
person who had just had major surgery
and is in the elevated age range it
struck me as a reasonable response but
whether yeah totally correct response or
not hard to say oh yeah I know I mean it
did a lot of things it did it you know
there was a open source information
discovery effort I mean there's more
information flowing a torrent of
information flowing on the pandemic in
comparison kind of the black box in kind
of the black box trickled that we got
into in previous events you know and
this information is constantly being
vetted it's being torn apart reassembled
new strategies are being produced
information is then you know turned into
knowledge and and you know insight that
the consensus puts into play it's it's
pretty pretty amazing process to watch
you know and given that it's really
truly early days I mean you know the
consensus ideas stretches back to the
big open source protests that we saw
back in you know the Arab Spring all the
way up through we saw it just recently
we saw it in Puerto Rico where they
toppled the Governor of Puerto Rico I'm
coming together over a single idea so
these these
a contestants can mobilize very very
quickly and they can you know undertake
an incredible information discovery
effort and it can implement and act on
that in a very complex way you know far
faster I think then and you know the
older traditional government can't but
there's also a need for the dissent and
if you have too much dissent it seems
chaotic in the last three years or so
you know with with Trump in power it
felt more chaotic than than stable but
that doesn't mean that we should not
have the dissent because the consensus
can get locked in and we're gonna find
that out going out of this trying to get
out of this lockdown is that it's going
to be very hard to get people out of the
kind of siege mentality that developed
as part of this consensus and that the
dissent is one of the keys to kind of
getting us out of that and you know
constantly arguing in favor of moving
the economy forward but you know we're
gonna have to figure out other ways to
break out of it
this is this lock-in achieved by the
consensus yeah that's interesting and as
we were chatting prior to the to the
going live on the show you made the very
good point that like what did you make
the point about the attributes of this
particular virus and how its kind of a
perhaps a challenge for Network sense
making yeah this virus is just like this
perfectly designed instrument for you
know sitting astride just you know
obvious need for a complete lockdown if
it was really really truly deadly up to
2030 percent or you know just letting it
go through with with the kind of a herd
immunity strategy you know it targets a
very specific subgroup so most people
under 50 are not really impacted that
that much and that gives a you know a
false sense of kind of immunity to the
to the effects of the virus and then it
requires a you know incredible
investment a time to kind of eradicate
it with it you know two weeks of
quarantine and the necessity of doing
that early and what else about this I
had a whole brief that I wrote up on
this that you know this the design of
this virus it makes it really really
effective and then the the speed of
transmission is is absolutely insanely
I I mean it's up in small parks
territory according to some estimates
exceeding smallpox less than chickenpox
so you can you know get out of control
very very easily and and zoom to you
know population scale levels yeah it
makes decision-making on this very very
hard and you were mentioning that it was
between these two valleys they it's it's
it's it's interesting to see us kind of
grapple with that made that incredibly
hard for the government to make
decisions because it's really not clear
exactly what strategy exit strategy or
response strategy is the best do you do
full quarantine where you do do do you
do kind of a big tech testing regime to
kind of stabilize the situation or do
you go with hurt immunity I've been
evaluating all three of those and I've
kind of come to a conclusion on that but
we can get to that recently about the
Swedish experiment with herd immunity
yeah well one of the themes that we see
in the in the dissent is that herd
immunity is probably better as a
strategy because you know shutting down
the economy for months at a time is is
just not sustainable it's cause more
damage long-term than been suffering
through a couple hundred thousand dead
and so I went in and I looked at kind of
the exemplar of the of the strategy
Sweden and I found out that they were
really very similar to what we see in in
many states with a couple exceptions is
that they have not closed elementary
schools and activity so there is a
transmission vector but you know the
evidence is that the elementary school
kids don't carry high viral load so it
probably isn't as big of a vector as you
would get if you had universities still
open and that they use let cut bars and
restaurants stay open but the bulk of
the the actual mitigation of the virus
is all being done but through social
distancing and Sweden is really quite
good at social distancing I mean there's
always a joke about you know I saw
pretty interesting a joke about that is
that if you want to really experience
loneliness you know standing a bus line
in Sweden because everyone six to seven
feet away from each other but I started
looking at you know what the impact of
just letting this roll through the
population and assuming that you can
using social distancing and in in
selective government efforts to kind of
mitigate the effects to keep the level
of people who are sick below the level
of the capacity of the health system
because and the strategy and the herd
immunity strategy is that you as long as
you can care for these people
effectively is in the health care system
you'll let it run as hot as possible for
as long as possible until you achieve
her an immunity status and what that
means is typically for something that's
the respiratory virus that's highly
transmissible somewhere between eighty
and ninety five percent of the
population has to get it and then
recover from it and have some kind of
internal immunity and evidence suggests
that there is you do get him become
immune if you recover from it
now that strategy and as I looked around
the world and found out or found where
the virus is having the most impact is
that it works and it probably will work
in relatively young countries and I mean
with their median age of less than
thirty and that it proves to be deadly
in countries where the median age is
greater than thirty and you have the
places where the virus is having that
most deleterious impact is it in the old
developed countries you know old sick
developed countries the fragile
countries of you know China and the US
and Europe
you know median age is 38 38 and 42 and
EU a lot of really really old
populations are and what the virus did
is it turned our health care system
witches are you know considered our
strength and one of our key strengths
into a weakness weakness so so big that
it made us fragile it you know allowed
us to keep a lot of people alive longer
but
accumulated chronic conditions so in the
u.s. we have upwards of 45% of the
population has least one chronic
condition that they're dealing with
according to the CDC so in that kind of
population old and sick when you start
to get to try to get to the 80 to 95
percent immunity level required for
Humanity
it gets really deadly very quickly so I
did the calculations on what it would
require best case to the United States
is that we have upwards of two to two
and a half million people would die from
the virus in order to achieve herd
immunity because it would have to impact
the at-risk populations in order to
achieve it that would be running the
current levels at five to fifteen
thousand people a day dead for a couple
hundred days yeah that's not gonna
happen that's politically not palatable
even and the other course even though
people point out some of the more
hardcore herd immunity people that the
actual number of lost productive years
will be surprisingly small because the
typical person who actually dies is like
78 years old and has an estimated two
years of life left nonetheless
politically and from a humanitarian
perspective that just isn't gonna fly at
all particularly if the alternative is
something you know in the 200,000 deaths
range so so yeah I think I agree with
you so my intuition was correct to act
as if lockdown was the right strategy
that's good to hear yeah I mean in
places like India in the population over
65 is 6 percent it's tiny you know it's
herd immunity is possibly it will burn
itself out you know go our Oh less than
1 pretty quickly because I mean there's
just so many young people that it runs
into that it doesn't really have an
impact that life expectancy is short
there so the number of people that are
80 with compounded complicating factors
is small too right so and so that's
where the real death that's where the
real harvest comes late seventies onward
with complications oh yeah the way I
just looked
by the internet the median age in Sweden
is 41.1 so probably not a good place to
be running the herd immunity experiment
correct unless you are unless you're a
little fascist you're trying to cleanse
the body the National body and make get
to make it a little bit stronger no with
less less deadweight but that's the yeah
I'd like in Germany for instance you
know forty i think forty eight percent
of the people that have died or over
eighty that's typical x78 is the best
guesstimate of in the West at where the
average age of tau all these will be
right and so it's it's interesting that
you know the strength gets turned into a
weakness you know and it makes herd
immunity impossible which is usually you
know at a gut level this is kind of what
the way we've handled respiratory
pandemics in the past you know we've let
herd immunity take care of it because we
were younger and healthier in it and it
you know allowed us to do so but yeah it
doesn't work now that the quarantine
strategy that china file it doesn't
really work either
i mean because it's just so deleterious
there it's so negative in terms of its
impact on the economy and you keep that
fragility in place even though you kind
of externalize the quarantine meaning
that if you can eradicate it internally
then you have to shut down your borders
in order to prevent any any new virus
from you know entering back in already
the chinese have you lost what they were
ruining at a negative seven percent
according to this morning's figures for
their economy so the first time it's
gone negative in fifty years according
to chinese stats the ours is likely to
go down minus thirty probably by the end
of the second quarters that put that in
comparison yeah i think they're i think
they were you know this is chinese stats
right and they increase their death toll
by fifty percent too but it's not it's
still you know radically understating
the actual negative impact but it you
know quarantine strategy really is in a
good long-term strategies particularly
if we don't develop a vaccine or
effective treatment for a corona virus
this is kind of like yes
you know solving the common cold to a
certain extent we haven't been able to
do that for years and ever really end
we may not get that with this so that
leaves only one strategy left and this
is the one I'm working on today is a I
call it the big tech solution and the
reason I call it big tech is that is you
know kind of a testing case tracking
monitoring solution but the only way you
scale it particularly to a population as
big as we have in the u.s. is through
tech and the key think to that the
cornerstone to that the thing that
actually could turn our population
making it's like adding a network
decision making system kind of taking
the consensus and articulating it with
technology and then saying okay we can
turn our population into something smart
enough that this virus this pandemic
isn't a problem anymore I mean it's like
an annoyance and to do that you would
need to do in-home medical monitoring
use the smartphones from honoring you
know a lot of big data and individual
decision making systems built-in to get
control of the information environment
regarding health regarding a
transmission of a virus in this virus
and and combine that with state level
hiring of case trackers and people to
handle the monitoring and etc etc but
that kind of effort could pull off a you
know a long term solution that actually
allows us to operate as if we didn't
weren't even threatened by the virus
anymore weren't even threatened by the
pandemic but the big problem with that
obviously is that the we have almost
zero trust in any effort to aggregate
data
you know we've lost that trust funny I
don't because I I worked in the direct
mail business in the 90s and I realized
by 1996 with what the data aggregators
had Axium etc there is no privacy so
fuck it right just go yeah privacy you
know it's it's a it's all hung up on
this idea that you know we've been you
know strip mined for data by the the big
tech companies and then before that the
direct marketing companies for four
decades we don't have any trust in any
of those companies to provide to do
right by us regarding the data and we've
kind of treated data
which is one of the most valuable
resources in the world it's you know
it's it's a product of you you're it's
like a piece of your labor as something
that's valueless I mean it's valued by
all the companies that can grab it but
our only solution to it is to treat it
you know to apply privacy to it which is
really just destroying the value of it
and the what we need to kind of get over
this lack of trust in the government and
lack of trust in corporations is this
idea that you actually own your data
yeah that's clearly the right answer
right personally I would sell all my
health data for $5.00 right because I
believe that health data is more
beneficial to the Commons than the
privacy of it is worth to me right but
other people might make different
decisions and it doesn't really matter
that's the key thing about the dance on
the back side of this curve is you don't
need data from a hundred percent of the
people you need statistically valid
sampling data and it may well on a
population of let's say at the state
level three or four million you may need
a few thousand people providing high
fidelity data to give you a sense of the
the native incidence rate and and have
the powers-that-be be able to respond
forcibly to a local flare-up so the idea
of personal ownership of the data and
voluntary opting in for a consideration
and then licensing to the commonweal for
you may be for only a specific use only
say to some consortium of Apple
Microsoft and Google who is doing
monitoring for kovat and oh by the way
this grant has a time to live of one
year and if you violate it there's a
$250,000 penalty right something like
that would make great sense and then you
then if some people want to be paranoid
about their data oh let them let those
of us who are more realist about privacy
and the relative benefits of at least
some data in the Commons opt that way
then we'd get a clearer signal and it
would make managing this very very
practical oh yeah I mean there's a way
to kind of accelerate it though I mean
I've been pushing kind of because the
scale of the crisis this emergency you
bi kind of thing but we change that to
kind of like
a kind of a pandemic response payment
you know a thousand bucks a month for
contributing the data for participation
to do the individual health monitoring
the kind of you know temperature checks
on a daily basis all the stuff that
you'd opt-in with using the smartphone
you get ninety ninety five percent
participation rates and you'd get data
down to such a granular level and it
would be going in and you get paid for
it and with set expectations that you
would actually get paid for your data I
like it I like it a lot
let's talk briefly about ubi and one
other very interesting topic you and I
both like you be I think in concept but
the more I've thought about it respect
to this particular pandemic the less I'm
convinced that an ongoing ubi is the
right answer at least in the form it's
currently being implemented which is a
electronic transfer to your checking
account because we go back to the 2008
financial crisis we found that then more
than 70% of those stimulus checks like
was it twice they were sent out ended up
going into people's savings which makes
sense you know when when the system
seems under stress when uncertainty is
high those people who have jobs and have
at least a little financial buffer will
tend to add net liquidity to savings and
that's indeed what I expect will happen
with this one so 70% of this large
amount of money is essentially waste
it's not truly wasting so there's a
little bit of impact on behavior but not
much and as you know you've heard me say
before that if we could send these
things out as debit cards that had a
time to live 45 days and if you didn't
spend the money on the debit card 45
days it evaporated back into the
Treasury's pool of money to be
reallocated the following month then I
think a ubi could be very stimulative to
the economy but since no one seems to be
running with this debit card idea
probably the smarter thing to do is
massively augment unemployment checks
maybe just increase them by 50 percent
or a hundred percent because why yeah
well there are they doing an actual I
know they're extended the term yeah and
I think it's some places they're upping
well anyway that's where all the money
should go shouldn't go into UVI unless
you can find that way to have it have a
time to live so it gets spent into the
economy and not just saved much better
because most people a lot of people a
huge number
tragic number of people have lost their
jobs and will continue to lose their
jobs over the coming forty five days or
so the vast preponderance of people
still have their jobs probably eighty
percent so they don't really need the
UVI in fact that we rank Li we're
probably all financially but we still
have our jobs or our sources of income
are actually better off because we're
spending a shitload less right think
about how much money people wasted going
out to our restaurants and bars you know
I remember when I was 29 years old it
was a non-trivial percentage of my total
income you know currently we're at home
eating beans and rice so people's
expenditure has gone down their income
eighty percent of people's incomes
haven't of employed people so there's
really not a need for a ubi but let's
focus at all unless we can have time to
live let's focus it on the unemployed
yeah you know I've found that there are
response at least at the bureaucratic
government response to this crisis has
been been terrible because I think it
the scale of it the timeframes are so
short the scale is so large that they
really just flubbed it they just even
you know the complete bipartisan
cooperation can't get it done I mean
that two and a half trillion for
actually four and a half of you taken
all the money relief bill was an example
of just total disaster I mean yeah the
rules weren't simple yeah oh yeah and
the SBA stuff I mean I mean the Small
Business Association I mean what
ninety-six percent of small businesses
didn't get anything I mean it was rated
by the big companies uh it just wasn't
thought out it you know they tried to
make it nuanced they tried to make all
the nuance they try to add to this from
the means-testing to the the
conditionality is just working against
them and this is why I focus on a very
simple solutions that work this is a
whole network disaster and we need a
whole network response we need to reboot
the whole thing and the thing with the
EBI is that you know the bottom or the
top 10 percent don't need it granted and
they wouldn't need it afterwards either
they're gonna do fine it's the bottom
90% and in more than half of them
supposedly have no savings and what this
does is that it is an income replacement
it's taking off some of the sting and it
allows you to borrow for short-term
needs because you have a kind of a you
know ongoing payment that can be
borrowed against probably a pretty
reasonable terms and it allows you to
plan for the future I mean it it is you
know what sings you know that this money
is coming in and you get a job and is
supplementing your income and you get a
big boost in your income you know for
the for the at a thousand bucks a month
in a you know to income earner family
that's upwards of a 50 percent
improvement over there the median income
for the country it was it would be a big
boom and people could plan against that
they would spend the money they would
feel more confident I you know I think
the the big psychological effects at the
network scale are going to be extremely
important in terms of us getting out of
it because you know in the previous
crisis in the financial crisis it took
forever to get out of the kind of siege
mentality that that we had due to that
due to that event and that was this much
smaller event than this you know I don't
want to spend a decade crawling out of a
depression Airy economy I mean because
the the social cohesion factors alone
are going to be extremely dire I agree
there exactly on the same page that the
team red team blue shitshow of the
stimulus was nearly as bad as they could
make it you know the Dems demanded cover
bunny for government oh yeah that'll be
really useful right and then the
Republicans baby along lobbied for
corporate welfare so both of them are
wrong yeah yeah the cool thing about a
consensus and dissent framework is it
makes it really different from the old
left-right framework that you used to
have the left-right we use the you know
big government small government values
associated with each
consensus to set framework is detached
from specific policies or to attach from
specific value sets the consent conform
/ owned anything whatever is opposite
could can do it yeah we need to give
those that maybe the right answer is the
problems the network doesn't have its
levers on power directly right wouldn't
it be clever if you know that somehow
the network and the dissent both could
allocate the stimulus money for instance
right something like my liquid democracy
ideas where you know people vote how
they want to vote they proxy to people
who know more than they do
and then you know let's say the dollars
are at the end of the day allocated by
the number of votes that no final leaf
level proxy holders hold and they caucus
and they choose things to spend the
money on something like that would be
very interesting but you know today the
network does that work and the dissent
is not directly coupled to the levers of
power that's a political power yeah but
it means shut down the US economy and
it's gonna keep it shut down until it
decides that it wants to you know to
release it that state and the the states
and and the federal government really
can just cajole them can make their
arguments in favor of easing up but the
network is gonna make the final decision
it's most powerful thing and then they
you know they the federal government
could have shut shut down the economy I
mean even if it tried I mean it just
could not do it as quickly and as
effectively as the consensus did yeah
and in fact this actually reminds me of
in nineteen sixties saying by the New
Left radicals which was vote with your
feet in their sense they were saying
quit your job and go become a hippie
essentially in this case people voted
with their feet by not going to work not
going shopping and not getting on
airplanes it's kind of very cool that we
happen to be in a decision frame where
we could actually vote with our feet and
it might be useful think about other
scenarios we're voting with your feet is
is viable let's move on to my last topic
here is a few minutes which to my mind
one of the most entry
seeing things that's happened in the as
we start approaching the peak here and
soon to the managing the backside of the
curve is the emergence of the state
regional compacts as the way to
aggregate learning and coordination on
the gradual reopening I got to say it's
like Churchill said in his history of
World War two then he hadn't had a good
night's sleep from May 1940 until
December 7th 1941 at Pearl Harbor where
he knew World War two had just been won
by the Allies I had a similar reaction
the day the two compacts were announced
I said holy shit
maybe we will actually do a tolerable
job of reopening the country in a
nuanced regionally sensitive data-driven
scientific fashion rather than relying
on the shitshow in Washington what are
your thoughts on these regional compacts
and what might they mean for the future
well you know one of the ways that
decision-making systems handled threats
they can't handle is that they
decentralize say you know in this case
the level of governance that actually is
effective it you know was found at the
state level and that I guess at the
regional block level in terms of what
they're doing and they're sharing
information sharing resources but you
know they may accrue power you know over
time remember they're extra
constitutional so there is a kind of an
open-loop element here if it lasts a
long time and these are you know these
blocks prove effective we can see you
know a lot of power accumulating in them
and it may change you know the way the
nation is run I mean they're all around
you know 50 to 60 million people which
is seems to be kind of a more effective
level of you know where the government
actually can can make effective
decisions you know over 300 million it
becomes just too complex a problem given
that the the speed and scale at which
these network threats emerge there was
also a layer that I was surprised that
no one
see well maybe it's because they don't
understand the way that dynamics of this
stuff works is that there was a there
may be even still is an opportunity to
kind of grab the baton and the consensus
a bit but it has that you know it's like
running a kind of a daily program
focused on specific things said we can
all do together I mean there's lots and
lots of spare capacity in the consensus
to get things done kind of a kind of
open source manager sort of speak who
focuses on tangible near-term steps that
can be taken in order to achieve the end
goal is eradication of the pandemic and
you know not any of the you know the
standard political elements anything
that's divisive just focusing on things
that you know everyone can agree on
because it achieves that goal like for
instance our local makerspace which I
helped get started is working on its own
in coordination with the two local
hospitals to build face shields building
by the thousands right they ain't no
politics involved there this is
basically pure grassroots a community of
makers who have access to some amazing
tools figured out first they did some
prototype sent him over to the hospital
said no not quite right what we really
need is this and within a week the
makers figured out what the hospitals
need bought some materials and they're
stamping them out by the thousands right
yeah perfect yeah that could also that
all could be brought to a national level
I mean you look at the White House
briefing and it's about marshalling the
the federal resources are not ret
marshalling the federal resources to
solve the problem but kind of like a
counter-programming maybe live on
YouTube for an hour every day where you
have some kind of celebrity emcees that
kind of we're not celebrities from
Hollywood but you know maybe political
talent that that's willing to kind of
step into the space that in an
relatively non-political way and then
kind of MC an hour to of you know
highlighting specific projects that like
the one you mentioned and bringing it to
a national scale and monitoring its
progress and and telling people what
they can
you know and to contribute and to get
get things done and it could even be
information discovery you know it's you
know what what new information do we
need in order to make more effective
decisions and having 10 or 20 million
people working on it you can get it
solved really really quickly and it's a
it's a resource that we haven't really
tapped into and it could be you know if
you could you know somebody moved into
that space that it could yield a
incredible amount of political power
going forward damn great idea people so
social entrepreneurs out there who have
a decent followership on YouTube or
something let's run with let's run with
this idea let me know I'll promote it
I'll help you bring in guests and
commentators and things like that I
think it's a great idea and that you
know there's there's just like I can
just see it now there's a vacuum waiting
for this to happen somebody ought to do
this whether it'll happen right now or
not because of the time is hard to say
but it ought to yeah I agree it well
that's just a an opportunity that would
have been better and filled if it was
done last month when people are still
scrambling okay I will point out this is
one of the things I've been hitting
regularly is managing the back side of
the kerbs could be a shitload harder
than managing the front side as it
turned out there was one brute force
rubber hammer that worked which was
social distancing period really that's
the only thing that worked and if it
hadn't been for that the whole medical
system would've been overrun sort of
their weak-ass response on ventilators
and PPEs would not have even come close
to do the job so a d- job on
mobilization in terms of equipment and
protocols etc was saved by one big brute
force hammer there is not a brute force
hammer on the back side of the curve
it's a very nuanced that sophisticated
dance and so the need for these things
may actually be greater on the back side
than there was on the front side as it
turned out right yeah that's the back
side the exit strategies are tough in it
that's why I'm leaning towards the big
tech thing it's a the two other
solutions are too brutal and it makes a
fragile kind of developed countries
ambulatory for the next you know decade
right I can't see us getting out of it I
mean no unless there's something out of
the blue tech fix in terms of vaccine or
treatment
it's absolutely brutal unless we kind of
adopted the big tech fix as I earlier
there is one other one which I actually
think it's worth considering which is
the Paul Romer insane level of testing
Thanks which could be the two could be
combined Paul Romer the Nobel
prize-winning economist has done some
very interesting modeling which says if
we do the number sounds insane
22 million tests a day right so every
adult gets tests every two weeks and
that there was essentially instantaneous
contact tracking and quarantine on the
back side of that maybe publicly paid
foreign teaming at hotels which will
still be underutilized for a long period
of time then we could get back to pretty
close to normal more or less instantly
might take us three months to ramp up
that level of testing if we made a world
war two level of commitment to it but
that's what I think I like about it it
doesn't require any new computer systems
it doesn't require any money to
cooperate it's a very brute for if it
makes cooperate the level if you want to
keep your job you have to be tested it
works right not coercive but pretty damn
persuasive or not mandatory but for any
damn persuasive and when I look at the
things that need to be done
brute force just like social distancing
has a big plus which is that it could be
executed by the morons who run our our
systems there's some problems with
obviously because I mean that's the kind
of thing you have to do every day
potentially for a decade I mean this is
a pandemic and it's not gonna go away
globally it's gonna keep on coming back
and we're even having problems now
getting beyond the 150,000 tests a day
level so I mean they're automating it
and then you know that will allow us to
reach higher levels but that's an
incredible amount of scale it is easier
look at one or two how many fucking
tanks did we build look us a while to
ramp up but we were putting them damn
things
every few minutes right but I think we
have to think about all these yeah I
will say that I you know having done IT
development at very large scale during
much of my career you know anything that
requires a lot of data a lot of data
processing user interfaces etc it takes
how fuckload longer than you think make
bulletproof etc and it might actually be
ramping up testing I don't think any 22
million a day but say five million a day
may be actually done much more faster
and we'd be robust
well anyway John as always incredible
the interesting conversation here which
I hope our audience will appreciate and
I'll remind people to check John out at
Global guerillas on patreon put a few
arms in his cup so he can continue doing
his work and let's do this again soon
all right Jim thanks production services
and audio editing by Jared Jane's
consulting music by Tom Muller at modern
space music.com
[Music]